GRAPHIC COMMUNICATIONS INTERNATIONAL UNION, LOCAL 259-M RECORDS (APAP021) 1941-1988
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Graphic Communications International Union, Local 259-M Records1941-1988
nam_apap021
This collection includes records from Graphic Communications International Union, Local 259-M and the three previously independent unions that merged to form GCIU Local 259-M - Utica Graphic Communications Union, Local 58-C; Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union Local 21-P; and Local 59 of the Amalgamated Lithographers of America (ALA).
International Printing and Graphic Communications Union
5
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Graphic Communications International Union, Local 259-M allowed its original records to be microfilmed by the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives. After microfilming, the originals were returned. 1989-1990
Biographical History
The Albany Photo-Engravers Union No. 21 was chartered in 1921 as an affiliate of the International Photo Engravers Union of North America (IPEUNA). Local 59 of the Amalgamated Lithographers of America (ALA) was chartered in 1943 with a single shop and approximately 50 members.[GCIU, Local 259-M. Dinner Journal (20th Anniversary of Local 59), [1963]] In 1964 IPEUNA and ALA merged at the international level to form the Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union (LPIU). Local 59-L merged with the Albany Photo-Engravers Union No. 21-P, LPIU, to form Local 259 in 1966.[GCIU Local 259-M. Dinner Journal, 1966] With the merger of LPIU and the International Brotherhood of Bookbinders (IBB) in 1972, the local became Local 259-M (signifying "Merged") of the Graphic Arts International Union (GAIU). In 1983 the GAIU merged with the International Printing and Graphic Communications Union (IPGCU), Local 259 became an affiliate of the Graphic Communications International (GCIU). In 1987, the Utica Graphic Communications Union, Local 58-C (signifying "Commercial") merged into Local 259-M.
The Utica Graphic Communications Union, Local 58-C, was chartered in 1898 as Utica Printing Pressmen's Local 58 of the International Printing Pressmen and Assistants' Union of North America (IPPAU). When the IPPAU merged with the International Stereotypers', Electrotypers', and Platemakers' Union of North America (ISE&PU) in 1973, the local became Utica Printing and Graphic Communications Union No. 58 of the International Printing and Graphic Communications Union (IPGCU). When the IPGCU merged with the GAIU to form the Graphic Communications International Union in 1983, the local became the Utica Graphic Communications Union No. 58-C.[Fink Gary, ed. Labor Unions. Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1977, pp. 137-39, 300-04]
Local 58 was involved in a prolonged strike against the Utica Observer-Dispatch that involved four other unions. The strike was begun on July 15, 1967, by Local 58 when it disagreed with the newspaper over how many people were needed to tend a new press. The Utica Newspaper Guild No. 129; Stereotypers', Electrotypers', and Platemakers' Union, Local 46; and the Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union, Local 61, joined the strike afterwards. The Utica Typographical Union No. 62 observed the picket lines but never joined the strike. The five unions formed a joint committee during the strike and bargained with management together, although the Utica Typographical Union was the leader in economic negotiations.[The Guild Reporter, October 27, 1967, pp. 1 and 6] After 100 days, the unions received an improvement in wages that was also sought, and the strike (the longest in Utica's history) ended.
GAIU, Local 259-M, was involved in a noteworthy case against the Amsterdam Printing and Litho Corporation. The union had lost an National Labor Relations Board election in 1973, but it objected to the conduct of Amsterdam Printing and Litho during the election and another election was held. Local 259-M won that election and was certified as the bargaining agent for all lithographic production employees in the plant. The company refused to recognize the union and eliminated a Christmas bonus, changed wages, and reduced the workweek for its employees, all without consulting with the union. In 1976, the company was determined by NLRB to be engaging in unfair labor practices and was ordered to restore the workweek, pay all lost bonuses, pay for wages lost, and pay for the wages of laid-off employees up to the time the company began bargaining in good faith with the union. All these payments included interest. [GCIU Local 259-M. Subject Files. "Amsterdam Printing and Litho Corp.--Litigation over Refusal to Recognize Union--Folder 2, 1973-77."]
Scope and Content Information
Since GCIU Local 259-M is an amalgam of what were once three independent locals, it has records produced in all its incarnations. However, there is always a dominant partner in any merger and usually only the records of that partner are retained after a merger. Although there is a good deal of documentation from Locals 259-M and 58-C, only scattered contracts remain of LPIU Local 21-P. The bulk of the records in this manuscript group are those produced by ALA Local 59 and its successor organizations.
Of special interest in these records are the minutes, which are almost complete from 1947 (three years after Local 59 was chartered). Although there is documentation of the union's negotiations with many shops, those records dealing with Amsterdam Printing and Litho Corporation are the most extensive and potentially interesting. A large percentage of the records of Local 58-C deal with the Utica Observer-Dispatch, including material on the 1966-67 strike.
For other printing trade unions in the Albany area, see the records of the Albany Typographical Union No. 4; the Albany Printing Pressmen, Assistants, and Offset Workers Union No. 23-C, GCIU; Graphic Communications International Union, Local 10-B (Bookbinders); and the Newspaper Guild of Albany No. 34.
After this collection was microfilmed, the originals were returned to GCIU Local 259-M.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series: 1 - Minutes: 1947-1988; 2 - Subject Files: 1946-1988; 3 - Utica Graphic Communications File Local No. 58-C., GICU, Records: 1941-1986.
Series 1 - Minutes, 1947-1988
Series 2 - Subject Files, 1946-1988
Series 3 - Utica Graphic Communications File Local No. 58-C., GICU, Records, 1941-1986
Subject and Genre Headings
Labor; Albany, New York; International Printing and Graphic Communications Union; Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union; International Photo Engravers' Union of North America; Graphic Arts International Union; International Printing Pressmen and Assistants' Union of North America; Printing industry--Employees--Labor unions--New York (State); Labor unions--New York (State); Minutes; Correspondence; Contracts
Container List
- Minutes, 1947-1988; 1; reel of microfilm
  Arranged by type of meeting minutes and chronologically thereunder.
  Contains minutes of general membership meetings (1947-74, 1979-88) and minutes of the executive board meetings (1950-56, 1960-88). The earliest minutes for ALA Local 59 no longer exist, and there are two significant gaps in the minutes, but otherwise these are complete. No minutes for LPIU Local 21-P are included in these minutes. Local 59 was apparently the dominant union, and only its minutes survive. For an interesting comparison with the actual minutes, see the subject files for the agendas for meetings (1973-85) as kept by the president of the local.
  - Amalgamated Lithographers of America, Local 59 Minutes, 1947-1959 (Reel 1)
  - Amalgamated Lithographers of America, Local 59 Minutes, 1960-1964 (Reel 1)
  - Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union, Local 59-L/259 Minutes, 1964-1966 (Reel 1)
  - Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union, Local 259-M Minutes, 1967-1969 (Reel 1)
  - Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union, Local 259-M Minutes, 1970-1972 (Reel 1)
  - Graphic Arts International Union, Local 259-M Minutes, 1973-1974 (Reel 1)
  - Graphic Arts International Union, Local 259-M Minutes, 1979-1982 (Reel 1)
  - Graphic Communications International Union, Local 259-M Minutes, 1983-1985 (Reel 1)
  - Graphic Communications International Union, Local 259-M Minutes, 1986-1988 (Reel 1)
  - Amalgamated Lithographers of America, Local 59 Minutes of Council Board Meetings, 1950-1956 (Reel 1)
  - Amalgamated Lithographers of America, Local 59 Minutes of Council Board Meetings, 1960-1964 (Reel 1)
  - Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union, Local 259-M Minutes of Council Board Meetings, 1965-1967 (Reel 1)
  - Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union, Local 259-M Minutes of Council Board Meetings, 1968-1969 (Reel 1)
  - Lithographers and Photoengravers International Union, Local 259-M Minutes of Council Board Meetings, 1970-1972 (Reel 1)
  - Graphic Arts International Union, Local 259-M Minutes of Council Board Meetings, 1973-1975 (Reel 1)
  - Graphic Arts International Union, Local 259-M Minutes of Council Board Meetings, 1976-1978 (Reel 1)
  - Graphic Arts International Union, Local 259-M Minutes of Council Board Meetings, 1979-1981 (Reel 1)
  - Graphic Communications International Union, Local 259-M Minutes of Executive Board Meetings, 1982-1984 (Reel 1)
  - Graphic Communications International Union, Local 259-M Minutes of Executive Board Meetings, 1985-1988 (Reel 1)
- Subject Files, 1946-1988; 2
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Contains by-laws (1951, 1963, circa 1964, circa 1972, circa 1983), contracts (1946-48, 1951-52, 1955, 1959, 1961-65, 1976, 1986-88), correspondence (1948-49, 1951-52), arbitration material (1973-80), and agendas for meetings (1973-85). This series is a collection of different types of material, including records on dealings with companies and information on the structure of the local.
  - Agendas for Council Board Meetings, 1973-1979 (Reel 2)
  - Agendas for Executive Board Meetings, 1980-1985 (Reel 2)
  - Agendas for General Membership Meetings, 1973-1979 (Reel 2)
  - Agendas for General Membership Meetings, 1980-1985 (Reel 2)
  - Alfred Publishing--Organizing, 1985 (Reel 2)
  - Amsterdam Printing and Litho Corporation, 1980 (Reel 2)
  - Amsterdam Printing and Litho Corporation--Litigation over Refusal to Recognize Union (1 of 4), 1973-1975 (Reel 2)
  - Amsterdam Printing and Litho Corporation--Litigation over Refusal to Recognize Union (2 of 4), 1973-1977 (Reel 2)
  - Amsterdam Printing and Litho Corporation--Litigation over Refusal to Recognize Union (3 of 4), 1975-1977 (Reel 3)
  - Amsterdam Printing and Litho Corporation--Litigation over Refusal to Recognize Union (4 of 4), 1975-1980 (Reel 3)
  - Argus Press--Contract, 1987 (Reel 3)
  - Baronet Litho, Inc.--Contract, 1986 (Reel 3)
  - By-Laws, 1951; 1963; ca. 1964; ca. 1972; ca. 1983 (Reel 3)
  - Capital Newspapers Division, The Hearst Corporation--Contracts with LPIU Local 21-P, 1964-1965 (Reel 3)
  - The Color Shop--Contract, 1976 (Reel 3)
  - Committee to Elect Emery B. Miller for President, ca. 1987 (Reel 3)
  - Correspondence of ALA Local 59, 1948-1949 (Reel 3)
  - Correspondence of ALA Local 59, 1951-1952 (Reel 3)
  - Crest Litho Inc.--Contract, 1988 (Reel 3)
  - Dinner Journals, 1962-1987 (Reel 3)
  - Dodge-Graphic Press, Inc. Contract, 1988 (Reel 3)
  - Greenwood Company--Contract with ALA Local 59, 1955 (Reel 3)
  - List of Shops with GCIU Local 259-M Contracts, ca. 1988 (Reel 3)
  - The Maqua Company--Contract with ALA Local 59, 1951 (Reel 3)
  - The Maqua Company--Contract Meetings with ALA Local 59, 1959 (Reel 3)
  - The Maqua Company--Strike and Strikebreaking, 1970-1977 (Reel 3)
  - Merger of GCIU Locals 259-M and 58-C, 1987 (Reel 3)
  - Metro Data Repro Graphics--Contract, 1988 (Reel 3)
  - Saratoga Printing Company--Representation Election, 1973-1974 (Reel 3)
  - Troy Record Company--Contracts with IPEU and LPIU No. 21, 1946-1948; 1951-1952; 1961-1965 (Reel 3)
- Utica Graphic Communications File Local No. 58-C., GICU, Records, 1941-1986; 3; 2
  Contains contracts (1950, 1960-61, 1965-85), arbitration material (1941, 1946, 1950-53, 1962-71), hearings conducted by the local (1963, 1966-69), and a constitution (1977). Most of this material concerns the Utica Graphic Communications Local No. 58-C's dealings with companies (especially with the Utica Observer-Dispatch); however, the hearings contain interesting material about the internal politics of the local. No minutes of this local survive.
  - Constitution, 1977 (Reel 4)
  - Crowley Publishing Corporation, 1957; 1959-1960; 1962; 1965 (Reel 4)
  - Daily Star--Contracts, 1975; 1980; 1982; 1986 (Reel 4)
  - Dodge-Graphic Press, Inc.--Contracts, 1976; 1979-1980; 1982; 1985 (Reel 4)
  - Evans, David--Hearings Before Union, 1963; 1966-1969 (Reel 4)
  - Hughes, Leland--Hearing Before Union, 1963; 1967-1968 (Reel 4)
  - Jones Stephenson Company--Arbitration, 1952-1953 (Reel 4)
  - Merger Considerations of the International Printing Pressmen & Assistants' Union of North America, 1972 (Reel 4)
  - Metzler Printing--Contracts, 1979; 1982 (Reel 4)
  - Notices to Local's Members, 1983 (Reel 4)
  - Oneonta Star--Contracts, 1965-1984 (Reel 4)
  - Rome Sentinel Company--Contracts, 1961; 1972-1982 (Reel 4)
  - Scononda Press, Inc.--Contracts, 1968-1982 (Reel 4)
  - Thomas circa Peters Printing Co., Inc., 1959; 1972-1973; 1976-1977; 1980-1981; 1984 (Reel 4)
  - Thomas circa Peters Printing Co., Inc.--Contracts, 1967; 1979-1982; 1985 (Reel 4)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Arbitration over Contracts, 1941; 1946 (Reel 4)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Arbitration over Contracts, 1950-1951 (Reel 5)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Arbitration over Demand for Arbitration, 1965 (Reel 5)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Arbitration over Holidays, 1967-1968 (Reel 5)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Arbitration over Manning of New Presses, 1971 (Reel 5)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Arbitration over Overtime, 1962-1968 (Reel 5)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Arbitration over Overtime and Improper Relief from Duty, 1963; 1965-1967 (Reel 5)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Contracts, 1950; 1967-1981; 1984 (Reel 5)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Correspondence, 1960-1962; 1966; 1969; 1984 (Reel 5)
  - Utica Observer-Dispatch--Strike, 1966-1967 (Reel 5)